<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Foundational</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-12-16T09:41:11-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Charles Farr</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Right Sizing Mobility In Our Cities</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/right-sizing-mobility.html"/>
   <updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/Right-Sizing-Mobility-In-Our-Cities</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Merriam Webster defines &lt;strong&gt;mobility&lt;/strong&gt; in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the quality or state of being mobile or movable;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the ability to change one’s social or socioeconomic position in a community and especially to improve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the dictionary definition does not explicitly link (1) &lt;strong&gt;physical&lt;/strong&gt; mobility and (2) &lt;strong&gt;social &amp;amp; economic&lt;/strong&gt; mobility, it is easy to see how they are intertwined. If a citizen is unable to tap into the economic benefits of a city because their mobility is physically limited, this will impact their ability to change their social and economic standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, physical mobility is critically important for all citizens’ lives and is a key area of focus for governments large and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States today, physical mobility is achieved primarily by automobiles due to years of auto-centric transportation and planning policies. The result is the automobile has been and continues to be one of the most influential forces in American cities and Americans’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as we approach the challenges of the 21st Century — including combating climate change, reducing inequality, and fostering economic growth — reliance on automobiles alone seems to be an increasingly futile strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is the solution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that cities and towns need to foster alternative means of mobility, specifically people-centric modes. “People-centric” mobility modes are those that emphasize the pedestrian and their movement, without wholesale reliance on automobiles. In doing so, cities and towns will foster greater economic prosperity for their citizens, meet the tough climate challenges that lay ahead, and generally improve the quality of life of their citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does People-Centric Mobility accomplish all of that? First, let’s take a more in-depth look at the problems facing cities today before we jump into why People-Centric mobility is the right solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;downsides-of-auto-centric-planning&quot;&gt;Downsides of Auto-Centric Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States today, the car has shaped how we build our cities. Ever since the automobile’s mass production began at the start of the 20th Century, US cities have centered their approach to mobility on the automobile. The result is an urban landscape that prioritizes the automobile over all forms of mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many of America’s largest cities, over 50% of total real estate is dedicated to automobiles, either in the form of roads or parking. Estimates peg the total percentage of land dedicated to roads at 42% for Chicago, 37% for Phoenix, and 28% for New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the most car-centric European cities dedicate roughly 25% of land to car use, a proportion that is lower in many historic cities. In contrast, America’s allotment of space for cars is much higher. Meanwhile, dedicated bike infrastructure represents close to zero percent of land use in the United States, while public transit also commands a relatively small percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This auto-centric approach to planning was driven by a booming 20th Century economy and the idea of the “American Dream.” Now it has left cities to deal with a gloomier reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-levels-of-congestion-impacting-cities-productivity-and-citizens-wellbeing&quot;&gt;High-levels of congestion, impacting cities productivity and citizens’ wellbeing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that Americans spend 100 hours sitting in traffic each year, valued at an estimated $88BN. For an average American, that equates to ~$1,500 per year. The impact is worse in the most congested cities: $2,000+ per year in Boston, Chicago, Philadelphia, and New York. Leading urban planner &amp;amp; economist Alain Bertaud describes congestion as “as a tax on cities’ productivity” in his book &lt;em&gt;Order Without Design&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of congestion is not solely financial. Congestion also increases the total air pollution and greenhouse gas emissions and increases the negative health benefits of prolonged time spent in a car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The congestion in the United States is generally caused by an over-reliance on cars and the lack of alternative mobility means. The emergence of new rideshare and e-commerce business models has increased the number of commercial vehicles on the road and contributed further to congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;decreased-pedestrian-safety-resulting-in-an-estimated-66k-pedestrian-fatalities-in-2019&quot;&gt;Decreased pedestrian safety, resulting in an estimated ~6.6K pedestrian fatalities in 2019.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the Governors Highway Safety Association estimated that ~6.6k pedestrians were killed in fatal interactions with automobiles, representing 17% of total fatalities from automobile accidents (~39K total). This represents a significant increase from a decade prior when pedestrian fatalities accounted for only 12% of total fatalities. Further examining the increase, pedestrian deaths grew by 69% while cyclist deaths rose by 48%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increase in total pedestrian fatalities is driven by an increasing number of vehicles on the road and an increase in those vehicles’ size. These two trends are rooted in auto-centric planning policies, which prioritize automobiles’ movement at the expense of pedestrians’ safety (walkers, bicyclists, transit users, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-inequitable-mobility-distribution-predominantly-impacting-black-and-hispanic-households-and-their-exposure-to-economic-opportunities-in-the-city&quot;&gt;An inequitable mobility distribution, predominantly impacting Black and Hispanic households and their exposure to economic opportunities in the city.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In American cities today, Black &amp;amp; Hispanic households are less likely to have access to automobiles and quality public transit, mainly due to racist policies implemented throughout the 20th Century.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research from the Center for Neighborhood Technology (CNT) has found that Black households living below the poverty line have access to 7% fewer transit trips per week than white residents. Additionally, the routes these households have access to are less likely to operate on a high-frequency schedule. Furthermore, CNT found that Black households have less access to bikeshare and carshare than white and when utilizing rideshare services (Uber &amp;amp; Lyft), African Americans’ experience longer wait times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of mobility alternatives is especially impactful as car ownership looks very different for White, Black, &amp;amp; Hispanic populations. 40% of Black &amp;amp; Hispanic households living in poverty do not own a car, compared to 28% of white households living in poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This inequity in mobility distribution results in communities of color having less access to employment and labor markets via public transit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CNT found that across a sample of 10 large US metros African Americans had 31% fewer jobs requiring an associate’s degree or less than whites. The study also found that ~40% of African Americans and Hispanics living in poverty who rely on public transit must commute for at least an hour to get to their place of employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-levels-of-greenhouse-gas-emissions-contributing-to-climate-change-and-impacting-the-united-states-ability-to-meet-its-obligations-under-the-paris-climate-accord&quot;&gt;High-levels of greenhouse gas emissions, contributing to climate change and impacting the United States’ ability to meet its obligations under the Paris Climate Accord.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, personal vehicles — cars &amp;amp; trucks classified as light-duty — account for 16.6% of greenhouse gas emissions in the United States, accounting for 59% of total greenhouse gas emissions from transportation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decreasing this total is paramount to meeting the United States’ commitment previously made at the Paris Climate Accord. Unfortunately, electric automobiles alone will not decrease these emissions, so long as the current power grid draws on natural gas and coal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-levels-of-air-pollution-resulting-in-significant-health-impacts-and-premature-deaths&quot;&gt;High-levels of air pollution, resulting in significant health impacts and premature deaths.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers at Duke estimated that air pollution will cause 4.5 million premature deaths, 3.5 million hospitalizations, and 300 million lost workdays over the next 50 years in the US. Transitioning away from the usage of fossil fuels, a large part of which is emitted by transportation, would prevent these impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting economic value from mitigating these huge losses in life and productivity would pay for the energy transition to sustainable sources alone and would help the US stay below the 2°C pathway required to combat the worst impacts of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-right-sizing-mobility--people-centric-mobility-look-like-how-do-we-get-there&quot;&gt;What does Right-Sizing Mobility / People-Centric Mobility look like? How do we get there?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing the challenges of congestion, pedestrian safety, inequity and inequality, contribution to climate change, and air pollution is critical for cities if they hope to continue to grow and thrive. I believe cities should make “right-sizing” mobility a cornerstone of their strategy to address these issues, supporting a transition to a more People-Centric Mobility paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does People-Centric mobility look like and how can cities work towards it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, “People-centric” mobility emphasizes the pedestrian and their movement, moving away from reliance on automobiles. This definition includes walking, micromobility (such as bicycles 🚲, scooters 🛴, moped 🛵, tricycles &amp;amp; quadricycles 🛺, mini-cars 🚗, clown cars 🤡, and other yet-to-emerge form factors 🚜).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People-Centric Mobility is also multi-modal, meaning travelers use various modes to complete a given trip. As such, People-Centric Mobility also includes public transit 🚃. Public transit extends the ability to use other People-Centric forms of mobility (like walking or bikeshare), allowing residents to travel further in the same amount of time and contributing minimally to pedestrian safety issues, GHG emissions, and air pollution while actively addressing mobility inequality and congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building towards People-Centric Mobility requires broad policies to support the numerous forms of mobility under its umbrella. The good news is that these strategies are often complementary — policies to support pedestrians often benefit both bike riders and public transit users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;four key pillars&lt;/strong&gt; of a right-sizing strategy, including…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-build-better-pedestrian-and-bike-infrastructure&quot;&gt;(1) Build better pedestrian and bike infrastructure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building dedicated bike infrastructure &amp;amp; bikeshare programs induce demand for cycling and increase safety for cyclists and other road users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the construction of additional roadways induces demand&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the construction of bike infrastructure induces demand for cycling and micromobility modes. Therefore, it is critical for cities to build dedicated bike infrastructure to encourage more cycling and mode-shift away from driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to inducing demand for cycling, dedicated bicycle infrastructure helps directly protect cyclists from cars. It also boosts drivers’ awareness of cyclists, which translates to further increases in cyclist safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to dedicated bike infrastructure, the deployment of bikeshare programs (including both docked and dockless) induces demand for cycling and raises drivers’ awareness, benefitting all cyclists’ safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-support-the-development-and-adoption-of-new-micromobility-modes-and-form-factors&quot;&gt;(2) Support the development and adoption of new micromobility modes and form factors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with additional dedicated infrastructure, the wide-scale adoption of bicycles for all types of trips faces hurdles. Most bikes lack carrying capacity, constraining bicycles’ utility for shopping. Cycling requires significant effort for longer rides, constraining bicycles’ utility for longer trip types such as commuting. Bicycles’ lack of protection from the elements results in seasonal ridership trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is the emergence of electric pedal-assist bicycles (e-bikes) and other micromobility form factors — such as e-scooters, cargo bikes &amp;amp; e-bikes, and mini-cars — can help overcome many of these constraints, resulting in greater adoption and a mode-shift away from automobiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-bikes are ideal for commuting as they decrease the overall strain required, lowering the barrier for potential users. Research conducted by bicycle insurance provider Bikmo found that 33% of surveyed individuals with e-bikes use them for commuting, signaling increasing adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cargo bikes and cargo e-bikes enable both personal and commercial users to complete trips that previously required a car or commercial vehicle. In Germany, IKEA has begun to rent cargo e-bikes to their customers for transporting larger goods home. In many North American cities, large parcel carriers like FedEx and UPS are testing cargo e-bikes for deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More innovation is on the horizon with new form factors. Germany’s ONO recently raised 3 million EUR to develop &amp;amp; deploy a new cargo e-tricycle, more closely resembles a small van than a bike. The new design is completely covered to ward out the elements while providing significant amounts of cargo capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Paris, Citroen recently deployed a fleet of their new Ami model. The vehicle looks like a mini-car but is technically a quadricycle, weighing in at under 500kg while topping out at 45kmh (~28mph). Due to its classification, it can be driven by licensed users as young as 14-years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-boost-the-service-levels-of-public-transportation-and-deploy-new-mobility-services-to-better-support-commutes-between-neighborhood-centers&quot;&gt;(3) Boost the service levels of public transportation and deploy new mobility services to better support commutes between neighborhood centers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that COVID has changed mobility patterns in cities today, a phenomenon that is likely to linger for the foreseeable future. As office leases run out and teleworking becomes more acceptable, commuting patterns will change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the need for cities to prioritize supporting mobility for peak commuters, those headed into central business districts of the city at rush hour, is decreasing. Contrary to hot-takes calling this the death knell for cities, it simply means that inter- and intra-neighborhood travel is more important, as people stay closer to home or jump between neighborhood commercial districts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support these new transit patterns, city transit agencies will need to adjust their approaches to better support off-peak travel and travel behind more dispersed locations. This may mean that scheduling is steady throughout the day and new bus routes are needed to better knit cities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new commuting patterns are great opportunities for cities to provide their residents with new transit options. Increasing integration of e-bikes into bikeshare fleets makes many of these inter-neighborhood trips easier, while the rollout of dockless e-scooters accomplishes the same for intra-neighborhood trips. Pairing mass transit and micromobility strategies can make cities’ mobility infrastructure more flexible and resilient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-incentivize-the-adoption-of-alternative-mobility-modes-using-both-subsidies-carrots--pricing-mechanisms-sticks&quot;&gt;(4) Incentivize the adoption of alternative mobility modes using both subsidies (carrots) &amp;amp; pricing mechanisms (sticks)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing consumers with subsidies for the purchase of electric vehicles has effectively driven EVs’ adoption. By doing the same for electric micromobility purchases, cities can encourage &amp;amp; drive the adoption of new form factors. The result is an increasing mode-shift towards alternative mobility modes for a wider range of trip types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less popular but likely necessary to seriously move the needle on automobile usage is pricing the externalities of automobile use and charging for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing along a portion of the externalized costs associated with automobiles and their use helps cities push citizens to be more cognizant of the trade-offs between different modes of mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As automobile ownership is significantly more expensive than People-Centric modes of mobility already, increasing the cost to better reflect the burden automobiles place on the built environment and the climate, more citizens are likely to choose cheaper means of mobility than do today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different pricing mechanisms available for cities to experiment with, including congestion fees &amp;amp; surcharges, parking fees (higher than today), curb-use fees, and broader carbon taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-pursuing-people-centric-mobility-a-worthwhile-strategy&quot;&gt;Why is pursuing People-Centric Mobility a worthwhile strategy?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pursuing these four pillars allows cities to address many of the pressing issues they facing today and, in many instances, represent small-dollar investments relative to massive new transportation projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dedicate bike and bus lanes can be piloted for the cost of paint and stanchions, while more permanent infrastructure is less expensive than most road repairs — all pail in comparison to the cost of new rail or subway lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of a People-Centric approach are varied…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;hanging-indent&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building dedicated infrastructure and raising the drivers’ awareness that they share the road &lt;strong&gt;boosts pedestrian safety&lt;/strong&gt;, driving down the fatality rate that has climbed higher and higher in recent years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing adoption and usage of alternative mobility modes leads to a &lt;strong&gt;decrease in greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/strong&gt; as people rely on automobiles less and less. An e-bike charged on a grid supplied by fossil fuels uses almost no fossil fuel, while an EV only cuts down on a portion of the emissions generated by an internal combustion engine car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase usage of alternative mobility modes also **reduces the total air pollution **generated by automobiles, leading to a more pleasant city environment and mitigating some of the health effects associated with pollution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better supporting alternative means of transit and new models for public transit &lt;strong&gt;increases the equity of a city’s mobility landscape&lt;/strong&gt;. As many low-income populations rely on public-transit and bicycles today, prioritizing their support will lead to increased exposure and access to economic opportunities across the city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decreasing demand for driving &lt;strong&gt;decreases congestion on cities’ roadways&lt;/strong&gt;, benefitting the drivers that remain with easier commutes. It is important to note that automobiles will still remain a part of American cities’ mobility landscape for the foreseeable future. Still, the hope is automobiles will be better integrated into the fabric of the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to addressing some of the most important issues facing cities today, People-Centric Mobility generates a number of secondary benefits…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;hanging-indent&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased physical activity and decreased exposure to congestion generate &lt;strong&gt;positive health benefits&lt;/strong&gt; for a city’s population. Active commutes are associated with better overall physical fitness while reducing the physical stress caused by commuting has both physical and mental health benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased numbers of pedestrians — including walkers, cyclists, and other micromobility users — &lt;strong&gt;generates additional economic activity&lt;/strong&gt; for business along pedestrianized sidewalks and streets. Contrary to business owners’ fears that the addition of bike lanes or parking removal will hurt business, these strategies have been shown to increase customer spending time and time again. Pedestrians are more likely to stop and shop than drivers who buzz by in their cars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undertaking a strategy to support People-Centric Mobility will enable a city to make headway in its fight against some of the biggest issues they face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it will help cities stand apart from their peers, which is increasingly important as the location matters less and less for work. As individuals choose where to live, the draw of firms will lessen, while the importance of wellbeing will increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities that prioritize People-Centric Mobility strategy will become more resilient in the face of the challenges they are facing and more productive, creative, and innovative, as they entice more and more movers to choose them over their others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;hanging-indent&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Auto-centric planning was used a bludgeon to destroy vibrant African American communities throughout the 20th Century. The suburbs, wholly dependent on the automobile to support commuters, enabled “white flight” and the economic disinvestment that followed. The urban highway and renewal projects that followed to support these new suburban commuters razed and further segregated thriving communities of color. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Induced demand refers to effect on demand for driving caused by the construction of new roadways. As road capacity is expanded, the additional capacity is quickly filled by new drivers. &lt;em&gt;If you build [highways], they will [drive],&lt;/em&gt; or some such. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
